Finding Aid for Henry Moore Bates papers, 1886-1950
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Moore Bates papers 1886-1950
Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.
851123 Aa 2
Professor of constitutional law at the University of Michigan. Papers include correspondence, reports, articles, speeches, photographs, and notebooks, relating to Bates' professional career, with material concerning activities of Ann Arbor National Defense Committee; life and career of Lawrence Maxwell, lawyer and U.S. Solicitor General in the Cleveland administration, funding and building the Michigan Union (1911-1918); Republican politics in the 1930's and 1940's; Franklin D. Roosevelt's attempt to reorganize the Supreme Court in 1937; and campus life at the University of Michigan during the first and second World Wars.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor Numbers 725 and 2285
The collection is open to research.
Henry Moore Bates (1869 - 1949) had a distinguished thirty-six year career at the University of Michigan as professor and dean of the Law School. Bates was dean for twenty-nine of those years from 1910 until his retirement in 1939. Bates specialized in constitutional law, was widely published, and his influence on legal education was known to be "nation-wide." Bates took an active role in committee and nation-wide activities. Locally, he was involved in the Ann Arbor National Defense Committee and in the building of the Michigan Union on the University of Michigan campus. Nationally, he was called to testify before the Senate Judiciary Committee on President Franklin D. Roosevelt's Supreme Court reorganization proposals in 1937. Bates was awarded an honorary degree from the University in 1941.
The Henry M. Bates papers include correspondence, reports, articles, speeches, photographs, and notebooks, relating to Bates' professional career, with material concerning activities of Ann Arbor National Defense Committee; life and career of Lawrence Maxwell, lawyer and U.S. Solicitor General in the Cleveland administration, funding and building the Michigan Union (1911-1918); Republican politics in the 1930's and 1940's; Franklin D. Roosevelt's attempt to reorganize the Supreme Court in 1937; and campus life at the University of Michigan during the first and second World Wars.
The papers are organized into Correspondence undated and 1886-1949, Michigan Union Building, 1911-1918; Committee of Nine on Mineral Law, 1927-1929; Miscellaneous Papers; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor National Defense Committee (Mich.); Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Maxwell, Lawrence, 1853-1927.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; Michigan Union.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Supreme Court.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Delta Phi. Peninsular Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1881-1890.
Contributors:
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971.; Aigler, Ralph William, 1885-1964.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Babst, Earl D., 1870-1967.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Beveridge, Albert Jeremiah, 1862-1927.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Bulkley, Harry C. (Harry Conant), b. 1870.; Burke, Edward Raymond, 1890-; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917.; Cook, William W. (William Wilson), 1858-1930.; Coudert, Frederic R. (Frederic René), 1871-; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Gay, Edwin F. (Edwin Francis), 1867-1946.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Holbrook, Evans, 1875-1932.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1841-1935.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Laski, Harold Joseph, 1893-1950.; McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Pattengill, Albert Henderson, 1842-1906.; Pound, Roscoe, 1870-1964.; Powell, Thomas Reed, 1880-1955.; Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942; Rogers, Henry Wade, 1853-1926.; Rutledge, Wiley Blount, 1894-1949.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; Sutherland, George, 1862-1942.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1907-1968.; Van Tyne, Claude Halstead, 1869-1930.; Voelker, John D. (John Donaldson), 1903-1991; Wheat, Renville.; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Woodruff, Roy Orchard, 1876-1953.; Harlan, John Marshall, 1833-1911.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Tintypes.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically. It covers a wide range of topics on legal and political matters and university affairs. A select index to correspondents provides access to some of the more significant correspondents.
  - undated (Box 1)
  - 1886-1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898-1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903-1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1917 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1917 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1917 (Box 1)
  - January 1-15, 1918 (Box 1)
  - January 16-31, 1918 (Box 1)
  - February 1918 (Box 1)
  - March-April 1918 (Box 1)
  - May-June 1918 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936 (Box 2)
  - 1937 (Box 2)
  - 1938 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1939 (Box 2)
  - April-May 1939 (Box 2)
  - June-August 1939 (Box 2)
  - September-October 1939 (Box 2)
  - November-December 1939 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1940 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1940 (Box 2)
  - July-September 1940 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1940 (Box 2)
  - January-February 1941 (Box 2)
  - March-April 1941 (Box 2)
  - May-June 1941 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1941 (Box 2)
  - 1942 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1943 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1943 (Box 2)
  - January-May 1944 (Box 2)
  - June-December 1944 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1945 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1945 (Box 2)
  - 1946 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1947 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1947 (Box 2)
  - July-August 1947 (Box 2)
  - September-December 1947 (Box 2)
  - January-February 1948 (Box 2)
  - March-April 1948 (Box 2)
  - May-June 1948 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1948 (Box 2)
  - 1949 (Box 2)
- Michigan Union Building
  The Michigan Union series includes correspondence and other material relating to the planning, funding and construction of the Michigan Union building.
  - 1911-1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914 (Box 2)
  - 1915 (Box 2)
  - 1915, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1916, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1917, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 1918 (Box 3)
- Committee of Nine on Mineral Law
  - Correspondence
    - 1927, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1928, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1929 (Box 3)
  - Papers 1928-1929 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Papers
  The Miscellaneous Papers series includes files on a number of legal cases in which Bates was involved, book reviews and articles, papers concerning the Bates memorial service and letters of condolence following Bates' death in 1949.
  - Homer Carey 1929-1932 (Box 3)
  - Concerning an independent Air Force 1947 (Box 3)
  - Nuremberg Trials, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Panhandle Pipeline Case 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Justice Holmes undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence concerning the selection of the dean of the Law School of the University of Missouri 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Committee on Foreign Relations 1946-1948 (Box 3)
  - Lawrence Maxwell 1944-1947 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Wine Tax Case
    - 1946-1948 (Box 3)
    - 1946 (Box 3)
    - Memo undated (Box 3)
    - Memo undated [rough draft] (Box 3)
  - Bates Memorial Service
    - Papers concerning the Bates memorial services 1949-1950 (Box 4)
    - Letters of condolence 1949
      - A-C (Box 4)
      - D-L (Box 4)
      - M-R (Box 4)
      - S-Z (Box 4)
  - Reports and articles 1914-1920 (Box 4)
  - Book reviews and articles 1937-1943, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1911-1949 (Box 4)
  - Notebook, undated, concerning partnerships (Box 4)
  - Federal Oil Conservation Board 1927-1928, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Bank of America Case 1939-1940
    - Papers 1939-1940, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Report, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Report 1940 [rough draft], 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Uniform Mortgage Committee 1922-1924, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports, Articles, Speeches and Notebooks (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits; tintype of Bates' father and photographs showing activities as student and as faculty member at the University of Michigan, including photo of deans of the university (1915).
  - Photos, 2 photographs (Box 5)